Affirmative Action, University Commission for; Records ua010.009
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University Commission For Affirmative Action Records
1975-1997
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua010.009
2 cubic ft.
Documents the University Commission for Affirmative Action, which "aimed to enhance the university's diversity among the student, staff, and faculty populations by developing structures and incentives that promoted gender, racial, ethnic,... equity among the university community".
Access
Access to these records is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives, University Libraries, University at Albany.
Administrative History
The University Commission for Affirmative Action was created in November 1976, and was charged to "advise the President, recommend policy appropriate to Affirmative Action, and assist the Affirmative Action Office in setting appropriate goals and assuring their accomplishment." The commission's creation was in response to the University at Albany's need to comply with newly created state and federal equal opportunity laws. The commission initially consisted of twenty-one commissioners, but the structure was revised in the 1984-1985 academic year and a nine person commission was established. The commission illustrated its commitment to affirmative action by selecting a diverse representation of members from the university's various colleges, schools, and administrative offices. Originally, the commission members served one year appointments, but later it was expanded to three-year appointments. The commission met biannually in the Fall and Spring, and reported "to the President its plans and progress, and made recommendations requiring action."
The commission aimed to enhance the university's diversity among the student, staff, and faculty populations by developing structures and incentives that promoted gender, racial, ethnic, [sexual orientation and disability] equity among the university community. The bulk of the commission's work was carried out at the committee level. The commission was charged with coordinating the implementation of the "Affirmative Action Plan," a document created by the Affirmative Action Office that detailed the policies regarding equal opportunity at the university, and the Affirmative Action Plan Committee was created in 1977? to insure its implementation. The commission focused on compliance with Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972, and recommended remedies based on the "Institutional Self Study." In 1977, the Women's Concerns Committee was formed to "develop educational programs for women;" the Committee created sub-committees such as the Women's Connection newsletter in 1979 to highlight activities of campus and community women's groups. The Grievance Committee was founded in 1977? to establish a panel to hear discrimination complaints.
The Network Committee was established around 1977 to publicize the activities of the Commission and the Affirmative Action Office. "TOP" Target of Opportunity Program was proposed in 1985 to increase faculty diversity at the University [Memo form Martone to Ramaley, UCAA 1985 folder, O. of Pres.]
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of materials created by various members of the University Commission for Affirmative Action. This includes meeting minutes, internal and external office correspondence, newsletters, and commission files all arranged chronologically.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Women; Affirmative action programs; Albany (N.Y.); Minutes; UAlbany Task Forces & Committees; Minorities; University Commission for Affirmative Action
- UCAA, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 1)
- UCAA, 1989-1990 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 2-4)
- UCAA, 1989-1990 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 5)
- UCAA, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 6-7)
- UCAA, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 8)
- UCAA, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 9)
- UCAA, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 10-11)
- UCAA, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 12-13)
- UCAA, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 14-15)
- UCAA, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (University Commission For Affirmative Action Recor), Folder 16-17)
- Waiver Requests, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Faculty Hiring Requirements, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Afirmative Action Goals, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Sexual Harrasment, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Middle Earth, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Executive Commission, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Executive Committee Meeting, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Executive Committee Meeting Agendas, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Executive Cmmittee Meeting, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- UCAA Executive Committee Agendas/Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- UCAA Executive Committee Assignment/Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- UCAA Waiver Requests, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- UCAA General Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- UCAA Committee Preference Lists, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- UCAA Agendas/Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- G. DeSole, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Statement of Organization and Goals, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Executive Committee Commision, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Affirmative Action Plan, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Executive Committee Papers, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Waivers and meeting Minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Executive Committee Papers, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Minority Concerns Committee, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- UCAA, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Affirmative Action Plan and Statistics, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Affirmative Action Plan, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Executive Committee Search, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Executive Committee Search, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Womens Concerns Committee Report on Sexual/Racial Harassment, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- UCAA Womens Concerns Committee Meeting Minutes, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- UCAA Womens Concerns Committee Meeting Minutes and Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- UCAA Womens Concerns Committee Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- UCAA Womens Concerns Committee Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 33)